Guide to the Richard W. Pollay papers, 1869-2000 and undated RL.11638
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richard W. Pollay papers
1869-2000 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pollay, Richard W.
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
RL.11638
5.0 Linear Feet
Richard Pollay was a professor and curator of the History of Advertising Archives at the Sauder School of Business, University of British Columbia. Collection includes slides, correspondence, poetry and short stories, posters and other printed materials. The bulk of materials relate to Pollay's research into advertising for 19th and 20th century patent medicines, traveling sales personnel, as well as support materials for teaching presentations along with a collection of plastic and plush toys representing advertising mascots and spokes-characters. Companies represented include A&W root beer, American Association of Advertising Agencies, Coca-Cola, Dole, Energizer, Harley-Davidson and Kellogg. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: General Files; Print Materials; Slides; and Toys, Advertising Mascots and Promotional Characters; and Audiovisual Materials
Biographical / Historical
Richard W. Pollay was Professor and Curator of the History of Advertising Archives at the Sauder School of Business, University of British Columbia. Born 1940, Connecticut; BA 1962 Rensselar Polytechnic; MA 1963, PhD 1970 University of Chicago. Assistant Professor, University of Kansas 1966-1970; Associate Professor 1970, Professor 1986, University of British Columbia.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Richard W. Pollay papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2008 and 2013.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Advertising Ephemera collection
Richard Pollay Acme advertising collection
Richard Pollay Tobacco industry promotion (TIPS) collection
Roy Lightner collection of antique advertisements
Collection Overview
Collection includes slides, correspondence, poetry and short stories, posters and other printed materials. The bulk of materials relate to Pollay's research into advertising for 19th and 20th century patent medicines, traveling sales personnel, as well as support materials for teaching presentations along with a collection of plastic and plush toys representing advertising mascots and spokes-characters. Companies represented include A&W root beer, American Association of Advertising Agencies, Coca-Cola, Dole, Energizer, Harley-Davidson and Kellogg. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Advertising; Advertising -- United States -- History; Advertising -- Canada; Traveling sales personnel -- Correspondence; Patent medicines; Toys -- Collectors and collecting; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; American Association of Advertising Agencies; Coca-Cola Company; Dole Food Company; Kellogg Company
- General Files, 1883-1988 and undated; 1
  - Commercial traveler poetry--Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Drummers and commercial travelers--List of companies whose representatives passed through St. John's, as noted in Gripsack magazine, 1890 (Box 6)
  - Drummers and commercial travelers--Verse and other narratives, 1883-1919; 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Drummers and commercial travelers--Verse and other narratives--Canada, 1888-1925 (Box 6)
  - Keeping Advertising from Going Down in History--Unfairly, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Medicine Men, Mountebanks and Madison Avenue--Source materials, 1911-1974 (Box 1)
  - Medicine Men, Mountebanks and Madison Avenue--Source materials, 1919-1967 (Box 6)
  - Recitations and yarns of drummers and commercial travelers, 1890-1910 and undated (Box 1)
  - Recitations for Knights of the Grip, undated (Box 1)
  - Working Paper 446. Life of a 19th Century Commercial Traveler: From Verse to Verse, 1977; 3 folders (Box 1)
- Print Materials, 1926-2000 and undated; 2
  - Advertising Age--50 Years of TV Advertising, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Advertising Age--50th anniversary issue, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Advertising Age--100 Leading National Advertisers, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Advertising Age--Fast Facts, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Advertising Age--House that Ivory Built (Procter & Gamble 150th anniversary), 1987 (Box 5)
  - Advertising Age--Market/Advertising Research supplement, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Advertising Age--The Advertising Century, 1999 (Box 5)
  - ADvertising Service for Students--Outstanding Advertising Case Histories, 1977 (Box 5)
  - American Advertising Federation--College chapter information kit, 1989 (Box 1)
  - American Association of Advertising Agencies--Advocacy posters, undated (Folder 1)
  - American Broadcasting Company--ABC Advertising Standards and Guidelines, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Creativity/Marketing--Annual Advertising Awards, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Ken Hudnall Yellow Pages Educational Fund--Yellow Pages Connection teaching and learning guide, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Madison Avenue Goes to War (Frank Fox), 1976 (Box 2)
  - Marketing Magazine--75th anniversary issue, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Marketing Magazine--90 Landmark Canadian Advertisements, 1998 (Box 6)
  - Marketing Magazine--Annual Marketing Awards, 1993-1998; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous print advertisements, 1926-1961 (Box 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes Ad Council, Erwin Wasey house ad, Fuller brushes, The Hucksters film, Young & Rubicam house ads (Shadowed, Supreme Court)
  - Sunkist promotional booklet, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Trevor Hutchings cartoons, 1984-1989; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Hutchings (d. 1993) was a cartoonist for Marketing Magazine, producing satiricial views of the advertising profession
  - VCU Adcenter--New student orientation materials, 2000 (Box 6)
- Slides, 1869-1990 and undated; 3
  - Advertising in the 19th century, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Advertising through the ages, 1869-1880s and undated (Box 2)
  - Green-washing and "green" advertising, 1989-1990 and undated (Box 2)
  - Original advertising, cinema and television, 1920s-1950s (Box 2)
  - Patent medicines, undated (Box 2)
  - Peddlers, drummers, commercial travelers, undated (Box 3)
  - Teaching exemplars--Campaign consistency 1, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Teaching exemplars--Campaign consistency 2, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Teaching exemplars--Sex and sexism, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Teaching exemplars--Truly creative 1, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Teaching exemplars--Truly creative 2, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
- Toys, Advertising Mascots and Promotional Characters, 1982-1997 and undated; 4
  - A&W, Chubby Chicken, undated (Box 7)
  - A&W root beer bear, undated (Box 7)
  - California Raisin, 1988 (Box 7)
  - Coca-Cola polar bear, undated (Box 7)
  - Dole Bobby Banana, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Energizer bunny with drum, undated (Box 7)
  - Green Giant "Jolly Green Giant", undated (Box 7)
  - Harley Davidson hog, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Hershey Chocolate bear, 1982 (Box 7)
  - Jack in the Box plastic mascot, undated (Box 7)
  - Kellogg Frosted Flakes, Tony the Tiger (Box 7)
  - Little Penguin, The Little Penguin Merlot foam toy, undated (Box 7)
  - Pink Panther, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Post Super Sugar Crisp, Sugar Bear, undated (Box 7)
  - Safeway bear "because I care", undated (Box 7)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1958-1978 and undated; 1
  - Coca-Cola Basic Training Program for Salesmen: It's an Everyday Job, 1950s (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL11638-PD-001)
  - Coca-Cola Limited: Sales.com, The Markets (English and French), undated (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL11638-PD-002)
  - Earl Nightingale Gives You the Strangest Secret; Columbia Records, 1958 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL11638-PD-003)
  - Golden Dozen; Columbia Special Products for Acme Markets, undated (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL11638-PD-004)
  - Music from Marlboro Country; United Artists Special Products Division, 1967 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL11638-PD-005)
    Elmer Bernstein compositions; theme and variations of music from the Magnificent Seven and Return of the Seven films
  - Music from Marlboro Country; United Artists Special Products Division, 1973 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL11638-PD-006)
    Side 1: Ballads; Side 2: Marlboro Country Suite
  - Puffy Sleeves and Other Requisite Foolishness: The Compleat Home Treasury of Time Radio Commercials (Bert Berdis and Dick Orkin, Young & Rubicam), 1978 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL11638-PD-007)
  - Ralston Purina presents Tom Mix, original radio broadcasts volume 1, 1973 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL11638-PD-008)
  - Remember How Great? Collector's item from Lucky Strike; Columbia Record Productions, undated (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL11638-PD-009)
  - Themes Like Old Times: 90 of the most famous original radio themes; Viva/London Records of Canada, 1969 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL11638-PD-010)